[Music]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet. SC radio brings you.
relevant and detailed discussions of software engineering topics at least once a month.
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash software.
for software engineering radio this is marcus Blankenship, my guest today is josh duty.
josh has 10 years experience working for talent development companies in roles from engineering tests to consulting and management.
today we're gonna be talking about salary negotiation.
during his 10 year josh has learned how companies manage compensation and negotiation.
josh is the author of fearless salary negotiation, which is available on Amazon.
welcome Josh.
hi Marcus, thanks for having me, it's great to be here.
first let's start with what is salary negotiation.
yeah good good question, I would say at the highest level salary negotiation is a conversation usually between a potential employee and an employer.
potential employer to try and discover what the best arrangement is that will make both the employer and the employee satisfied.
for that employee to do some job for the employer.
so that's real vague, but basically it's a conversation to figure out what's best for somebody when they're going to work for a company to make everybody happy.
so that they have a good arrangement is when do these conversations typically happen.
there are two kind of primary times that a something that most people would refer to as a salary negotiation would happen.
the most common one that people would think of as you know when you're changing jobs. and you've got an interview and then you get a job offer.
and then you have an opportunity to negotiate your salary to figure out what the best calm package you can get is before you start.
and then the other time that it's also a sort of salary negotiation is.
when a current a person who's currently working for a company might reach out to their manager.
or someone else of the company and say I'd like to talk about increasing my salary for you know these reasons.
so that's also a different type of negotiation, but it is a salary negotiation.
so those are the main two, when you're switching jobs starting a new job trying to figure out what your comp package looks like.
and then if you're happy at your current job and just trying to figure out if you can get a better salary then that would also be a salary negotiation.
is negotiating my salary the same as negotiating for other things like the price of a car, negotiating on a home price.
is it the same techniques or is there something different about it.
I think the answer is you know sort of yes and no in a way, all negotiations are sort of similar and usually have common characteristics.
but in many ways you know salary negotiation is unique for sort of almost intangible reasons. but a big one is just there's so much riding on it.
it's weird to think about but a salary negotiation could be sort of the highest dollar value thing.
that a person might negotiate for in their life other than maybe a house or property.
and so it's a big deal, but also you don't get many opportunities at it.
even a really kind of aggressive person would only negotiate salary you know let's say 10 times in their lifetime give or take.
so it's different in the sense that there's sort of more riding on it, and it feels like a heavier thing to do.
and it affects you know every two weeks you see the result of that negotiation in your paycheck.
I'd never thought about it being maybe the biggest one.
because over time it adds up to be such a large amount of money probably even in comparison to like your home or or other things.
I think for most people that's that's true.
you know if you think of like the kind of standard rule of thumb for buying a house is you know you you can borrow comfortably up to like two. and a half times your annual salary.
and of course I'm not commenting on whether I think that's good or bad advice, but you know two and a half times your annual salary you flip that over.
and what you're saying is sometime after the two and a half-year market a company you're probably earning more than the value of your home right.
so if you're at one company for three years plus then the salary negotiated will be the the kind of largest asset.
or the largest financial vehicle that you're working with on a regular basis.
Josh you brought this up earlier that a negotiation is a conversation to get to the best outcome, but best for who.
I often think about it is best for one side or the other, but is that always true.
that's a good question and I like the way that you you framed it.
I think a lot of people perceive salary negotiation to be I don't know something that you might see and like a like a movie.
you know it's an aggressive person slamming their fists on the desk.
but it is a conversation or maybe even a better word might be a collaboration where.
you know two parties are ultimately trying to figure out what makes both of them comfortable in a situation.
so for example it should be very difficult for a company to pay someone far less than whatever their their market value is right.
and that's because one person would be significantly losing out there in this case the employee.
and the flipside is it's pretty rare that a company will you know drastically overpay quote-unquote overpay.
for somebody in the sense that they're paying more than they can afford to or want to pay for that person.
and so usually that conversation is just about figuring out you know.
where exactly is the employer comfortable paying for the services the value that the person brings to the table.
and where is the employee comfortable providing that service for the compensation package that the company offers.
so this is just a really kind of classic example of the way that prices work in markets is.
you you know you find that the quote unquote market clearing price so where is everybody comfortable.
so I think there is a win-win there especially in a well done negotiation.
I think everyone leaves the negotiation saying on the employer side I feel good about the salary we're paying this person.
they've helped me understand the value they bring to the table.
and I as the company can see the value that they're bringing to the company and how they make the company better.
and from the employers the employees side excuse me they're saying I'm happy with this compensation package.
I'll be happy to show up for work every day to do a good job add value to the company.
and the salary negotiation is an - had that discussion before the person starts working.
so you get to that win-win before they actually start providing that by you and start contributing to the company.
the way you say it sounds really reasonable and yet conversations like this have been tough for me in the past.
I know your book is entitled fearless salary negotiation.
I'm clear I'm curious why you chose that title, why'd you put the word fearless in there or what does that infer.
right so I put the word fearless in there because I found that the topic of salary negotiation is intimidating to people.
and a lot of the conversations that I have even now as a coach I do a lot of salary negotiation coaching.
and if if not explicitly implicitly people I work with will express fear.
or that they're scared of something happening that is either out of their controller that is detrimental to them.
so really common fear with salary negotiation is if I negotiate they're gonna retract the job offer.
you know they're gonna the the company will just say whoa whoa whoa you know we made you an offer we're being very generous making this offer to you.
and now you're trying to negotiate it that's unacceptable offer revoked right.
and from the way I said that you can probably tell that I don't think that's a it's not a fear that comes to fruition ever.
if at all very rarely extremely rarely.
but it's a fear that virtually everyone has.
and so I wanted to get out in front of that.
and let people know that there is a way to negotiate salary fearlessly and get rid of those things that scare you.
and my entire strategy is built around what you described which is you know that conversation it's a collaboration.
and that's a lot of of what I'm trying to help people understand when I talk about the subject is look there's a process that you can follow.
and as an engineer somebody who is trained as an engineer I'm very comfortable with processes, and I think most other engineers are as well.
there's a process that you can follow that will get you better results by just taking concrete steps and doing discrete things.
and I can tell you along the way how we're mitigating risk at every step.
so that there's less fear involved in your scared which enables you to negotiate better on your own behalf.
which is gonna get you a better result in terms of compensation, and hopefully a better arrangement with your employer that everybody's happy with.
you brought up the idea of the framework set of steps an algorithm a few would be can you give us a high-level overview of what that process looks like.
sure so the negotiation step one or maybe step zero is actually during the interview process.
and it's usually in the pre-screen or what I call the pre-interview where the negotiation will start in a sneaky way.
when a company will ask a question that I'm sure most or all of your listeners have heard this question at least once.
and the question is usually something like so tell me about where you are right now in terms of salary.
and what you what you would like if you if you come to work for us.
so they're asking you for your current salary or your desired salary or both.
so that's kind of the for me the signal of the beginning of a salary negotiation.
because they're trying to sort of set a baseline that they can you know use later when they're making you an offer.
so the the first step to my salary negotiation method is do not disclose those numbers because it can only work against the candidate.
I have yet to find a really compelling reason that it works for the candidate.
and so that step kind of zero or step one is don't disclose your current or desired salary when asked for it.
and then you kind of fast forward so now you get past that kind of tricky part of the early interview process.
and you get into the interview process throughout that process my high-level strategy is your job as a candidate is to help the company understand that they will be better.
if you're a part of it.
and so the way I describe that is you're telling a story about how the company will be better if you're on their team.
and so that's through the whole interview process everything you do is designed to emphasize that.
and the reason this is effective is that remember you haven't disclosed your desired salary or your current salary.
and so what you're doing is convincing the company that one they should make you a job offer.
but two that they need to make you a strong job offer so when you see you're more compelled to come on board.
so you want to switch the company's thinking from what's the minimum that we can offer Josh to get him to take.
this - what do we need to offer Josh to convince him to take this job and get him on board.
there's a subtle difference there but it's a big difference in terms of the kind of offers that you'll get.
so once you get an offer just before you get an offer actually you want to do a step that I call setting your minimum acceptable salary.
and this is just sitting down and being honest with yourself and saying what's the minimum salary that I require to take the job as I understand it.
and you're doing this early so that your objective so your your judgment is not clouded by big numbers.
that might be thrown at you especially in terms of quote-unquote total comp.
so companies will offer you know not just base salary but they'll say your total comp is three hundred thousand dollars.
and they're rolling a whole bunch of things in there that are not things that you can pay your mortgage with like base salary.
so you set your minimum acceptable salary then you get an offer and now you have your baseline that you're shooting for.
which is I want to at least meet or exceed my minimum acceptable salary so that I have a win-win which is something you and I talked about earlier.
this is a way the employee can get to a win-win which is either don't go to work for the company.
because the company could not meet their minimum acceptable number.
or they do go to work for the company and meet or exceed their minimum acceptable number, both of those are a win.
because I think it's pretty obvious at least to me that if you can't meet that minimum then you shouldn't work there, it's not a good arrangement for whatever reason.
so once you have the number that they've offered you and you're ready to negotiate and you can negotiate in a way that will get you above your minimum.
then you're gonna counteroffer somewhere between 10 and 20 percent above their offer.
which again their offers floating because you have not given them things to baseline against like your current salary or your desired salary.
so they're making you an offer that's designed to convince you to take the job.
which is presumably somewhere you know in the upper end of the range of money they can offer you.
and then your counteroffer is designed to say well can you go a little bit higher in that range.
so you'll counter closer to 20% if you detect that the company really wants to bring.
you on board they're desperate to fill this position somebody just left two weeks ago.
and they have to fill it right now where productivity is gonna fall. closer to 10 percent if maybe you're just kind of feeling things out.
and they're feeling things out and there's no particular motivation for them to bring you on right now.
and they're just trying to see if you might be a in the future.
so once you've countered then they're going to respond to it usually they'll respond somewhere between your initial offer and your counteroffer.
and then you want to make sure that you kind of keep your foot on the gas negotiate all the way through the end try.
and push your base salary up the best you can.
and this is also the time when you get to negotiate fun things like vacation and signing bonuses and things like that.
and as you peg your base salary if the company doesn't come up to whatever you asked for there's an opportunity for you to say well I asked.
for this you didn't quite come up there can you do that base salary you just said and an extra week of paid vacation every year. and if you can do that I'm on board.
so once you've hashed out all those final details you've got a final comp package and usually you'll accept that package and start.
so that was kind of long-winded but that's an end-to-end salary negotiation strategy overview for you know what I would I do.
when I work with people and what I wrote about in my book.
that's that's fantastic just in hearing you describe it there were things you said that I internally thought to myself I'm not sure I could do that.
do you have if we go back to one of the first things you said which is.
when you're asked and this happens has happened to me and I suspect to a lot of our listeners.
when you're asked for your current pay or maybe your desired pay and I think both hi recruiters and the companies ask for this.
you suggest not giving this as a baseline number, how do you decline to provide that information what words do you use such that it doesn't shut the conversation off.
excellent question so I call it the dreaded salary question and just.
so you know to kind of zoom back for for everybody who's listening that question usually is phrased something like this.
so where are you right now in terms of salary and what would you like if you come on board with us what would you hope to make.
so that's the the two-part question that we're talking about here.
and essentially what they're saying is what is your current salary and what is your desired salary if you come on board.
so the way to answer this question kind of the first answer to this question the easy one is to take the current salary part.
I'm not comfortable discussing my current salary I prefer to focus on the value that I can add to this company and the opportunity that's in front of me.
so that's kind of a nice little script that you could use to to move on from the the current salary question.
and for the desired salary you can say I prefer to focus on the value that I can add to this company.
and I want this move to be a big step forward for me in terms of both responsibilities and compensation.
and so you're emphasizing to the company again remember in the interview you're telling a story about how the company will be better if you're a part of it.
a subtle way that you could do that is to say I don't want to disclose my desired salary.
because I don't know but I do want to focus on how I can add value to your company.
so explicitly saying you want to make the company better and I want to do that by taking on more responsibilities for you which is a good signal to send.
and I want my compensation to reflect that additional responsibility that I'm taking on.
so you're all you're doing the entire time is sort of pushing forward I want to move forward in responsibility and compensation.
so that's my kind of baseline script for addressing that question and it's that will work most of the time.
most of the time whoever asked the question will say no okay you know I tried.
but Josh isn't comfortable with that so you know moving on to schedule that first interview.
have you encountered situations where there was a second or third request for that maybe.
with under the idea of well I've got a I've got to write this on this form right.
this is a box I have to check and fill it in so I need to put something down here.
or is that just my fear coming through that they're gonna ask twice.
no that's that's not just your fear coming through that happens.
I wouldn't say frequently but it's not unusual and I find that this is a combination of sort of company policy and also the individual person that you're talking to.
some recruiters will sort of ask and I think they're just sort of asking because it's on their list of things to to do when you're screening a candidate.
is is you know take a shot at getting that information and if you resist one time they'll say yeah kind of shrug and move on.
some recruiters are a lot more aggressive and they'll say no I have to have this or we cannot move forward with this process.
I've heard that line a number of times you know kind of vicariously through people that I've coached.
and somehow it always sort of magically turns out that we'll look back later in the process and say huh we didn't end up disclosing that information.
and yet we were able to move on through the process even though they had to have that.
so I think it helps from the candidates side to think of this as a negotiation tactic because that's what it is.
they're trying to get information that they can use to make an offer again in the vein of what's the minimum.
that we need to offer this person to bring them on.
and I don't it's hard to say this without sounding like I'm sort of implying you know there's some sort of nefarious motivation here on their part.
they're just trying to look out for the company's bottom line and get a good value where they can.
and so that's what they're trying to do is what's the minimum that I need to offer this person.
and by telling them your current salary and your desired salary you're giving them.
really good data that will help them to determine what's that minimum you want to avoid that.
so that they think what do I have to offer this person to convince them to come on board.
and you're not giving them those kind of easy out cues of current and desired salary.
so if they keep pushing I found that you can you can give pretty compelling answers that are almost irrefutable and that most reasonable people will accept.
for the current salary I think a good answer is I don't want to tell you what my current salary is.
because that is you know sort of proprietary HR information about my current company and how they compensate their employees.
and I don't think that they would appreciate me sharing that information with a competitor.
which you're almost certainly interviewing with a competitor of some sort at least a competitor for talent.
I think that's a compelling reason and it's hard to argue against the sort of you know you're taking a moral stand there.
which is I'm just not comfortable disclosing proprietary information about from the company that I work for.
especially you know implicitly you're saying I don't know for sure that I'm gonna work for you. I do know for sure that my company would not appreciate me sharing.
that information that's almost always true unless you work for a company like buffer where this is all public.
and then on the desired salary side if they continue to push.
and continue to push I find that a good thing to say usually what they'll say is well I need to qualify you for a range.
so that we're not wasting anybody's time.
again if you frame this and you understand this a negotiation tactic.
then it makes it a lot easier to see what's going on there they're trying to get that number.
and so what you can say in response to that is okay well I don't know exactly what I would like to make but.
if you're trying to qualify me for a ring I'm happy to respond to that range and tell you if it's in the ballpark.
so that's usually sort of the hardest push that they'll make is I want to qualify you for range so we're not racing time.
a good response to that is okay why don't you tell me what that range is and I'll tell you if we're in the ballpark.
so then you know if I'm qualified or not qualified and we can just move on.
I like that answer by the way it's a little sneaky but by simply saying yes your range is in the ballpark you are not boxing yourself into that range.
and still leave yourself wide open to negotiate effectively later on while you know giving them what they quote-unquote need in order to continue the negotiation.
so that's kind of my long answer to how to respond to the dreaded salary question.
and while I'm thinking about it Marcus I'll send you a link I have an article that's that's written on that with that script that we talked about earlier.
and I'll share that with you so you can put it in the show notes or or use it however you like.
yeah we'll put that in the show notes.
Josh you've brought up two things here and I want to drill into them it was around the idea of ethical considerations almost are there ethics in negotiation.
I think there are ethics but I don't think it's a huge component.
I think at the end of the day a negotiation occasionally will veer into ethical territory.
usually the ethical things are you know about information disclosure and how this negotiation might impact parties who are uninvolved.
so you know again not disclosing my current comp because now I'm telling you what my current company pays people like me.
and that's useful information that could give you an advantage over them in some way.
and I don't work for you I work for them so I don't want to share that information.
but I see it it's much less ethical in moral than it is a sort of straightforward business value discussion.
and so they're you know are a lot of shows now on TV like shark tank and the profit in these shows.
and I think they're kind of helping make this clear to people who watch but you're just talking about you know the company's job is to make a profit.
you're a sort of job or role as a person is to make a living.
and so you're just having a business discussion about okay well how can I enable the company to make more profit in turn be compensated for my contributions there.
so I see it as a conversation a collaboration and in a business discussion between two parties who are trying to figure out what's the right arrangement here.
for us the business to continue making a profit or to make a more profit or do a better business because we're bringing this person on board.
and for the employee to decide you know what's the value of my time and my expertise to make me comfortable contributing to their goal of making a profit.
okay I have heard people feel sometimes that.
they were being greedy or maybe they were even being unethical by trying to negotiate for a good salary.
is there a sense of that it's not right to push too hard that it's not right to negotiate for a high salary maybe.
or is that something that is more a fear than it is a real ethical boundary.
I think it's more of a fear than a real ethical boundary.
I think that some crafty companies will sort of spin the negotiation as though you are having an ethical or moral conversation.
again I perceive that to be a negotiation tactic so this often happens with let's say small smaller companies and startups.
even recently I'm not going to name the company but I'm coaching somebody through negotiation right now with a public tech company that's doing pretty well.
and they're putting the pressure on in terms of well we can't we just can't really afford to pay you you know market rate because we're really strapped for cash.
and I think you know that that is kind of true but it's it's also a matter of understanding that the company is working to make a profit.
and when they're bringing someone in that person's job is to contribute to making it profit that's what shareholders want that's usually the end game.
so III think that it's more of a fear that people have that they might offend someone.
and that's them kind of projecting their you know negotiating with a company for a salary on to a recruiter that they're having a conversation.
with them feeling awkward about putting the recruiter in an uncomfortable position or putting the hiring manager in the uncomfortable position.
but you have to model that recruiter or hiring manager as a part of the company that they work for.
and and so I think that the more you see it as a process a business conversation then the more obvious it is that it's it's not an ethical thing.
it's not that you're trying to steal money from somebody you're trying to find the right price for the value that you bring to the company.
all right let's leave that topic and talk about market rate.
you've discussed this briefly use the phrase what is market rate and.
how is it important in salary negotiations.
so a market rate I I think this could easily veer off in a sort of.
like this kind of I don't know wonky economics discussion that would be really boring.
but I'd say it's a really highest level a market rate is just you know what's what's the typical amount that companies pay for somebody to do a job.
and bring the kind of skill set and experience to the table that you do.
so if we're talking about your market rate marcus's or Josh's market rate that market rate is.
what do companies generally pay for the expertise that this person brings to the table.
so at the highest level that's what it is and of course it gets a little bit more refined.
and so I break it down into three tiers they're sort of like what I call the industry market rate or kind of the broad market rate.
which is you know if we looked at everybody who's a software engineer.
and country with five years of experience in these technologies what's the market rate what are they typically getting paid.
and of course you can see right away that there are some problems there like well do they work in Miami or do they work in San Francisco. and the market rate is going to be different based on geography.
so then you can start to narrow it down and say well I'm gonna work for a company that's on the west coast.
or I'm gonna work for a company that's in the Midwest.
and so what's the market rate if I narrow it down from the high-level industrial rate to that geographic area.
which these days people work remotely and all these good things but I find that most companies are still more or less setting salaries based on where they operate.
because their cost of doing business is driven by the piece of property that they physically sit on.
and most of the people they hire will be from around that geographic area.
so you start with your in industry-wide mercury what's the general salary paid to somebody with five years of experience with this thing.
and then what are companies in this geographic area paying those types of people.
and in particular just companies if I can figure out you know maybe I meet someone at a trade show.
or a conference maybe I can find out even more detailed information.
about what specific companies that are similar to my company or the company I'm targeting what are they paying people.
and then the last level is if you can get it information on what is the specific company that I'm interviewing with.
or working at paying people with my type of experience in this industry right now.
so your market rate is it's a very sort of broad and and narrow thing at the same time.
it's broad in terms of what's what's the general average all the way down to what is this specific company pay someone with my level of experience.
and what I bring to the table to do this job.
do I need to know my market rate as I enter into a negotiation and and how does that affect what I say and.
do my expectations may be.
yes you should know your market rate if you can determine it and most of the time you can.
the reason is earlier when I gave my end-to-end overview of salary negotiation strategy I talked about the minimum acceptable salary.
so your market rate should impact your minimum acceptable salary meaning when you're deciding what is the minimum dollar amount that all accept to do this job.
a component of that is what is the market rate for doing the job and.
then you'll finesse it based on things you know about the specific company or the opportunity and things like that.
so you're a baseline for your minimum acceptable salary is your market rate.
so what does somebody that looks like me with my experience what are they making in this industry right now.
and then you would take that number as your baseline and say okay how excited am I for this opportunity what's the upside for my career long term.
how bad is the commute what does the team seem like what's the opportunity look like in terms of maybe getting exposure to new technologies.
or processes that I can't get at other companies and all those good things.
and you roll them all up together into your minimum acceptable salary before you get that job offer so you can position yourself for a win-win when you negotiate.
but that market rate should be your first step in setting your minimum acceptable salary.
so your minimum acceptable salary might be different per company it's not simply one number that represents you.
it sounds like it takes into it takes into account a lot about the the company that you're applying for that's right.
so I think that you can set sort of a broad minimum right.
so the minimum might be what is the amount of money that I need to bring in every month for me to provide for my family for example.
would be a nice way to think about a minimum but then you would say okay so I know what that number is.
and now I need to think about how do I adjust that number for this particular opportunity that's in front of me.
so I am coaching someone right now who's negotiating with two companies at the same time they've got offers in hand from both companies.
and we're trying to get the best offer from both companies.
and they have a different minimum for each company because the opportunities are drastically different opportunities.
and you know the short term and long term career effects are different the commute is different in all those things.
so you start with the kind of baseline and then you would have a minimum for each company that you're talking to.
you mentioned in your process you had a very nicely defined larger process for that.
you move through in in this is it different negotiating with a large company than a small company.
the answer is yes and no so the process that I described is effective for large and small companies.
but small companies and large companies usually have different things that are important to them.
and in particular I find that the larger the company you're working with and the more sort of opinionated about the negotiation the large company will be.
so some some companies will they prefer to negotiate on equity and it's hard to get away for that for example.
smaller companies also like to try and focus on equity but small companies tend to emphasize the fact that they're small they don't have a lot of capital.
and you know do you want to be a part of building something big as sort of a story that you have with smaller companies.
so broad strokes the process I describe is effective at large and small companies it's a it's built to be that way.
I spent a ton of time when I was developing that process that particular chapter on negotiating salaries from my book I rewrote it top to bottom three times.
because I wanted to make a process that could be more or less Universal.
and so it's designed so that if you use the process as I describe it it will be effective for you.
and I'm also finding ways that I can kind of finesse that process with different companies and different requirements.
and big and small companies do behave differently but the process itself is effective for for both large and small companies.
that's great it is there ever a time I shouldn't negotiate my salary.
you know I've thought about this you know off and on for since I started writing my book really because I advocate that you should always negotiate salary.
so I'm always kind of questioning absolute statements like that I have yet to find a situation where the answer is that you should not negotiate your salary.
and the reason is that if if you're following the process I described.
then you end up at a place where again the company is is making you an offer they're kind of making an offer not quite in a vacuum.
but they don't have those those handy-dandy guidelines to use in your current and desired salary.
and so they're sort of feeling out you know what it's gonna take to convince to you to come on board.
and your question as somebody who's received a job offer is always going to be okay that's a good offer but is it the best offer that I can get.
and the only way to really know if that's the best offer is to negotiate it.
and so sometimes it does happen where I'll work with clients will begin negotiating will do some things will get a firm offer in hand will negotiate that offer.
and what we'll find out is we have convinced them to make us the best possible offer and they will not budge on that offer.
and so the counteroffer part of the negotiation doesn't always move the needle.
but we did things up until that point to ensure that we did get to the place where we're confident that we've got the best possible offer in hand.
and so that's also salary negotiation so I think it's important to take kind of a broader view on salary negotiation.
the negotiation is not simply making a counteroffer it's refusing to disclose your current or desired salary setting your minimum beforehand.
it's excelling in the interview process it's sometimes getting companies to negotiate against themselves.
so there are ways that you can without countering offering you can get an offer to become a better offer from a company.
but the ultimate goal is to figure out what's the best possible offer that this company will make me.
in other words what's the most this company is comfortable paying me for the service and the value that I provide.
and that's your goal in the negotiation is to get there.
and so I think within that framework negotiating is always the right answer.
because even though sometimes you will run into a wall you'll find that you've maximized the potential there now you know that for sure.
which means that when you take that job you can be confident that I got the best possible offer that I was going to get.
I did the best I could in the negotiation and.
I can be confident that I want to show up for the first day of work there.
I didn't leave money on the table there inadvertently.
as somebody who's a been a poor negotiator with my employers in the past a lot of what you're saying is making me think back to times. when I didn't do these things.
and I don't know that I ever started a job resenting that I made too little but I certainly wondered if I could have gotten more.
do you find that if people don't negotiate and they simply accept the offer clearly your book everything about what you're telling us is we should be negotiating.
but is the downside to us not doing that just that we don't get as much money.
or is there a real fear that we might be resentful or unhappy at the new employer.
it's accommodate the two so I think you know everybody would prefer to know that they're making whatever their potential to make is.
especially when we're talking about money and paying bills and providing for a family and things like that I think it's important to have that peace of mind.
I also think you know so that's the kind of first part there but then there's also the regret piece that you mentioned.
where you might show up at a job and eventually.
if you're underpaid relative to what you could have commanded with a strong negotiation strategy you will probably figure that out one way or another.
like you might notice somebody who does the same job you do is driving a much nicer car than you are.
they could have gone in debt to do that but they also may just be making more money and can afford more car.
but you'll also hear you know sort of water cooler conversations sometimes things slip out and somebody may not say I'm making such and such amount.
but they might say something that you you know your your eyebrow raises and you say well wait a minute.
if that's true then he must be getting paid more than I am or she must be getting paid more than I am.
and so that's just not a good feeling to have.
so I think that there's you know you want to maximize the salary that you get paid.
but you also want to minimize the chance that you'll get into the job get six months in.
and realize oh man I left a bunch of money on the table.
and now that I'm at the company it's going to be challenging to make up that ground because of you know company dynamics and bureaucracy and those sorts of things.
I want to get into this idea of negotiating after you're at the company but before we drive that direction.
I'd like to briefly touch on the parts of the salary component that we have an opportunity to discuss in our negotiation.
you've mentioned a few non-monetary pieces I'm curious if you could kind of walk through do.
you have a standard list of those pieces that we can use as levers to move in our negotiation.
I do have sort of a standard list but I also defer to whoever I'm working with.
so I typically say you should start by focusing on base salary.
for me personally maximizing base salary rises above all else in terms of priority.
and the reason is that you can pay your mortgage with base salary you can make a car payment with base salary you can't do that with stock options.
and and so I usually start with base salary then there's paid vacation seems to be very popular.
I like that as somebody who thinks about dollars and cents and negotiation because the paid vacation time does have an actual kind of real-world value.
you know what a week of work is worth and so you know what the value of that vacation is.
and it's also more or less pegged to your base salary so those are the first two.
then signing bonuses and or relocation stipends for you know if I have to move across the country or relocate people like to negotiate on those.
and then you've got other much smaller thing like you know getting your company to pay your cable bill or your cellphone bill.
or if you work out of a co-working space getting them to pay that monthly lease amount.
and this is all done in I call it the final discussion but it's it's after you've counter-offered and the company comes back.
and says well we hear your counter we can't quite meet your counter here's what we're willing to do.
and that's when you kind of start going back and forth seeing how far you can push your base salary.
and then you work down you know the the first one or two things in your prioritized list of well if once I've maximized base salary.
if I don't get to where I want to get what are the other things that are important to me that I'll go after.
and like I said those are usually you know first is paid vacation and then we go from there.
as you talked through those I was imagining a previous employer a particular boss and the fear that at some point he would say it's just not worth it.
like I just we just don't need someone who's going to want to negotiate this hard and retract the offer actually came to mind.
you said you don't see that happen very often is it a real problem and if am I the only one that fears that.
it's a real problem in the sense that everyone is afraid of it so it's a it's a very common fear that people have that they're gonna negotiate.
and then the company will say I just don't want to deal with this person nevermind offer off the table.
so I think though that I can make a pretty compelling case that will help most people see why that fear is extremely unlikely to come to fruition.
so I'm hedging a little bit I can't say for sure that you won't run into a particular recruiter who just really had a bad week.
and they're just not interested in negotiating.
but I have not experienced this and with anyone that I've coached I haven't seen it happen.
right a lot of people have read my book I'm not getting you know emails for people saying I had a job offer retracted.
I got one email from one person who said you say that companies won't retract the offer.
if you negotiate I had an offer retracted when I asked some follow-up questions to understand their situation better.
trying to say this diplomatically I'm not convinced that the reason their offer was retracted was that they negotiated.
so that's one example out of I've sold hundreds of copies in my book right so it just doesn't happen.
however people are afraid of it and this goes back to the overarching reason for fear and salary negotiations which is we don't get many opportunities to do this.
you only get a few at-bats throughout your career you don't want to mess it up.
and so anything that we perceive as something that could cause the a deal to evaporate is a very big deal for us.
because that could be one of very few opportunities we have to get a good job.
and so I think it's a legitimate fear that people have because we understand how people work.
and we know that you know I personally would not like someone to negotiate against me if I offer them something.
but salary negotiations are different they're unique we're trying to find that that happy medium.
so why don't I think that companies are prone to retracting job offers the short answer is back to the company's job of making a profit.
dollars and cents are important to companies by the time you get a job offer from a company they have typically invested.
if not thousands tens of thousands of dollars sometimes in recruiting you.
and getting to the point where they have extended a real offer to you often just in man-hours they've usually burned thousands of dollars.
so you've talked to a recruiter for an hour - you've had you know one two three up to a dozen interviews with various hiring managers.
and sometimes people up to the you know SVP director c-level people those people's time is extremely valuable.
they've invested resources and you know posting the job requisition and all these other things they're spending lots and lots of money.
they might have flown you on site that could be thousands of dollars right.
and so you get to the point where they make you an offer they've invested significant money in getting to the point where they can make you that offer.
and so from their perspective this is a pretty big investment that they're making.
and so when they make you an offer they're not inclined to just basically light that investment on fire and get rid of it.
because you said you know you made me an offer I appreciate that I'd be more comfortable if we could do this other thing.
because you know back to my strategy I'm not pounding piss on fists on the table.
and demanding things I'm saying I would be more comfortable if we work together better if right.
and so you're collaborating with them.
so all that combined the huge investment that they're making upfront the fact that they have a real need to fill this position.
or they wouldn't be wasting their time talking to you.
and the fact that you're collaborating with them and just trying to find the best result results in.
just an extremely high likelihood that they're going to continue negotiating with you even when you counter.
and I would say the worst case scenario in 99.999% of situations is you negotiate you counteroffer.
and they say oh no we already made you our best offer we're not it's not negotiable.
and so now you know you got the best software possible you know what the offer is.
and you can choose to accept it or not usually based on your minimum acceptable salary.
so I think it's a real fear I think it's based on the way that we interact interpersonally with each other as humans.
but the dollars and cents for a business don't really work out for them to invest that much to get to the point where they make you an offer.
and then just pull the offer.
because you said you'd be more comfortable if they could adjust the offer in these ways.
that makes complete sense.
do do companies expect us to negotiate how do they view strong negotiators.
I think that most companies do expect people to negotiate or they at least allow for the possibility that you'll negotiate.
it's pretty rare that a company will make you their first offer will be their best and final possible offer.
I've seen it happen I've done it one time when I was a hiring manager there was one instance where I made an offer to someone.
and I said just so you know we think you're perfect for this position we're not messing around this is our best offer.
and I was being honest about that and we we ended up hiring that person at that.
rate.
how how do companies view good negotiators as it viewed as a negative thing.
or does it put them like do companies think wow this person will be like do they do they look on it as a positive attribute.
right that was the second part of the question yes so in terms of how companies perceive people who negotiate I think it's hard to say for sure.
I can make a pretty good case though that they would perceive someone who knows their own value.
and has made a strong case of the value that they bring to the company.
and then negotiates strongly on their own behalf I think most businesses were perceived that person to be a strong asset that they would like to have on their team.
because if they're this prepared for a negotiation if they're focus on understanding the value that they add.
then if they bring that same intensity to the job at hand they're going to be a good asset.
and so I think as I mentioned earlier businesses usually exist to make a profit.
and people who are business savvy enough to negotiate a salary in an intelligent.
and collaborative way are probably going to be the type of people who have skills that only enable the company to make more profit using that skill set.
so I think you know unbalanced companies would perceive a good negotiator.
so again not somebody who's just pounding fists on desks and making demands but you know collaborating and doing a strong negotiation standing on the interview.
they would perceive that person to be an asset that they would like to bring onto the team.
whereas people who don't negotiate I wouldn't say that it's a red flag.
but you miss an opportunity to show what you can really do in terms of thinking through hard problems and negotiation.
it's a is a challenging problem to solve it's challenging to do it well.
and if you can demonstrate that you can do it well be intentional with it have good reasoning make good arguments.
then I think that's a good signal to the company that this is a competent business person who could come in.
and bring some business acumen to whatever job they're doing.
when I was a hiring manager of Engineers we definitely thought that the engineers who could negotiate well were an asset.
we felt like their ability to persuade and think through and have tenacity and.
know what they wanted those were the kind of people we wanted at our company.
so I think many engineers as you say are afraid that they'll be considered high maintenance or difficult if they negotiate or it'll look bad upon them.
and yet for me I what you say really resonance resonates the opposite it was true.
we looked upon those people even if we ended up paying them more or maybe.
if we didn't there the fact that they were approached the situation that way was a very positive thing.
I'd like to turn now to the other time you mentioned when we will be negotiating.
we've talked a lot about when we join a company that initial offer but once you're in the door and having spent 14 years of an enterprise company.
I spent far more time getting salary increases than I did my initial sort of onboarding.
so I'm curious let's talk about that.
opportunity sometimes annually to negotiate your salary at the evaluation or the raise time.
is there an opportunity to negotiate because that's my first question I don't know that I ever perceived there was.
when I worked at a large company but what is your experience show.
I think you came at this question from exactly the right perspective which is most people are aware that there's an annual opportunity to.
if not discuss compensation to adjust it at most companies.
and the question about whether that's a good time to discuss a raise.
or to negotiate is based on a couple of things but the big one is is there budget available.
and that question will have different answers at different companies.
um first let me take one step back and just say to be clear we're talking about not your standard sort of you've been here another year here's one.
and a half or two percent thanks for being part of our company.
but we're talking about I want a ten percent raise for fifteen members I want a market adjustment I want something to say.
you know my salary is out of line with the value that I added I want to make a significant adjustment not just a sort of boilerplate standard adjustment.
so the the way that you know whether or not it's sort of negotiable in that particular window is is there budget for it.
and a good rule of thumb for whether there's budget is essentially does everyone in your company go through.
that process you describe the the the raise the merit increase performance review process at the same time every year.
or is it done ad hoc or is it based on anniversary date from when people are hired.
so if everyone is going through that process at the same time every year more likely than not there's going to be a fixed budget at the corporate level.
that is then kind of sliced up by let's say business division or Department and then sliced up again by manager.
and so there's not quite fixed but more or less fixed budget that's available.
and so and this is a case where it is of zero sum so in that case if I get a 10% raise and ever the average raises 2%.
either one person is the several people are gonna get nothing.
or a lot of people are gonna get slightly less than 2% to compensate for the wreck.
that I'm the fact that I'm gobbling up some of that budget for my 10%.
so there's the answer is there's really not additional budget or real budget available for you know market adjustments and large raises to negotiate.
so that's not a great time to pursue that on the other hand.
if you're either ad hoc which means some companies are going to the system where it's just sort of you come talk to us.
when you'd like to talk about arrays.
or we'll schedule some time with you if we have a performance review feedback for you.
or if it's anniversary which means you know every year on the anniversary of your start date we're gonna evaluate your performance and talk about salary.
then usually there's not a fixed budget and so you can kind of make your own budget or make your case for your own budget to be allocated.
so it's a little bit more let's say bureaucratic there's more red tape more approvals that need to be done.
but there isn't that sort of fixed budget that you're fighting for a piece of and instead you can kind of make your own budget.
so that's the first levels is their budget how do you know a good rule of thumb is.
if everybody in my company gets raises and promotions at the same time probably not budget there.
so you should go off cycle wait till six months out right in the middle between those two and there may be budget there.
and for everybody else if it's ad-hoc or anniversary based there probably is budget.
so I think that that was more or less your questions when's the good time to do it.
so yes you can negotiate for higher salary you should wait until there's a budget.
I think the last thing I'll say on that is you should also be aware that you mentioned being an enterprise for 14 years.
so I'm not sure if your company was like this.
but a lot of larger enterprise companies will have created essentially a rubric that they'll use to decide.
how much of a raise any one person in the company can get at a time.
so I worked at a large enterprise company where the answer was if you move up one pay grade for a promotion you can get a 4% raise.
if you move up to pay grades to get a to pay grade promotion you can get a seven and a half percent raise.
anything above seven and a half percent it wasn't impossible but it was really hard to do without kind of moving mountains.
and so that's something that really helped to be aware of.
and hopefully your manager can tell you is are there strict constraints on the amount of a raise that someone can get in one move at this company.
or is it all kind of handled ad hoc. is that okay to ask.
yes usually you know if you're pursuing a raise or promotion you'll put together a case.
and before you kind of send that written case you'll talk to your manager and have a conversation.
and say here's what I'm my goal my goal for this job title that I'm pursuing.
or this raise amount that I'm pursuing you know here's why I think I've earned that goal.
can you tell me what we can do to make this happen and what sort of timeline we're looking at.
and so part of that conversation would be hopefully collaborating with your manager to see what's available.
and then finding out oh is there some sort of system in place a framework that prevents someone from getting an extraordinary raise at this company.
and most of the time your manager will know that and will be able to either find out or communicate it to you.
it's pretty rare that that kind of thing is totally secret.
and so in that conversation you can usually learn that from your manager if that's the case.
now at the enterprise you're exactly right that I work dad we have an annual evaluation there was an annual time for a salary increase.
and it was a salary pool so I took a piece of the pie.
but I am hearing more and more and you mentioned this companies began small don't have this regular schedule of times to discuss it.
instead they leave it up to the employee.
if you do work someplace without a regularly scheduled time to discuss salary and increases how do you know.
when you should do that and how do you open that conversation because it seems kind of intimidating right.
so this is where my my method is built for this situation that you described.
so when I'm coaching people or you know I teach a class sometimes to kind of walk people through this process.
the taking control of that situation and making a good case for yourself is paramount.
and you may bump into these other constraints but the ability to do that effectively is is what's key.
and the way that you do that is by essentially reverse engineering the raise or promotion that you're pursuing.
so I can kind of talk about both at the same time raises and promotions are in my mind they're separate things.
I wrote them as separate chapters in my book but the process the actual steps that you take to get a raise or a promotion are virtually identical.
and so in both cases where you start is what is it specifically that I'm asking for.
what is the target job that I believe I'm ready to be promoted to what is the target salary that I have in mind.
and of course that target salary would be based on your market value research.
and things like that but the idea is that you want to know specifically what you're asking for.
the main reason for that is you want to make it easy on your manager.
so Marcus you were hiring managers he probably had some of these conversations.
it's much easier to talk about raises and promotions with somebody who comes to you.
and says I would like a raise to this amount or I would like a promotion to this job.
then it needs to talk with somebody who comes to you says I want more money right.
it's it's hard to have that conversation because the first question is well how much more and why those are the two questions that the manager has.
and so your job as an employee who's seeking a RZR promotion is to make that manager's job as easy as possible by setting a very clear goal.
and then before you ever have that conversation making a very good case that you have already demonstrated that you've achieved that goal that you're ready for that goal.
so in the case of a promotion it's sort of easy I mean it's not easy to actually execute but it's easy to envision or to plan for.
and that is what's the next job in my career path or what's the job that I'm targeting.
if I want to kind of make some move outside of my career path into a different area what are the responsibilities associated with that job.
and what's the difference between those responsibilities and my current jobs published responsibilities.
that difference that Delta between the job you're targeting and the job you're doing that's the stuff that you need to do to demonstrate that you're ready to be promoted.
this may be a little counterintuitive I think to people I think people like to believe that companies promote based on potential.
and you know this guy is a real go-getter and so I'm gonna just go ahead.
and promote him into this job that's above his current job and he'll grow into that role.
that almost never happens again looking at it from a managers perspective the manager is looking for somebody who can demonstrate that they can do the job right now.
because managers are busy people and there looking for things to help them be better at their jobs.
and manage their resources better in terms of you know what's available at the company.
so you say your your goal and then you make a case that I've already done everything I need to achieve that goal.
I'm already doing the target job that I'm going to ask my manager for.
or I can demonstrate very clearly that this raise I'm asking for is already justified by the work that I'm doing above.
and beyond what was expected of me last time my salary was set.
so as I'm talking you can probably see kind of like I said reverse engineering this idea.
that you know what am I going to ask for specifically and then what is the evidence that the thing I'm asking for is currently deserved right now by me.
and when you have all those things sort of packaged up and ready to go then you can go talk to your manager.
and say I would like a promotion to this job because all the reasons that I've demonstrated I'm already doing that job and I'm ready for the promotion.
or I would like a race to this amount because.
and you list all the things you're doing to add additional value to the company to your team to save money.
or make extra money for the company or the team since the last time your salary was set.
so in and that's the my process or my method in a nutshell is set your target do the work to demonstrate that you have already achieved that target.
and then you're essentially just going to talk to your manager to say here's what I've done here's.
what I would like to do to make it official can we talk about a timeline for making that happen.
yeah as a hiring manager I certainly found was much less risky to promote someone who I could see was taking the initiative.
and doing the job without asking for me to give them a pay or a title change upfront.
rather than someone who said well I'd like to be a tech lead make me that and then I'll start doing this job.
there's a lot of pieces to the job that were subtle and intangible and were mindset shifts.
and I think those were the things that when I saw them even if they weren't able to delegate out to the team because they weren't that position yet.
there was a lot of ways they could be doing things to show me that they were serious and ready for that.
my guess is though not all people listening like they have the ability to start doing the job they want.
are there tips or things you can recommend Josh that would move people in that direction even if they're not.
then manager even if they're not the product donor or whatever the new role is that they want to do.
yes definitely so when you've done what we described which is set your target and been identified.
if we're talking in particular about a promotion then you identified specific responsibilities that the job you're targeting requires in the job description right.
and so you'll find that those responsibilities that you need to accomplish will they'll usually fall into one of two categories.
one of them is kind of the easy stuff which is the stuff that you can do without any support.
so you know just just things that don't you know for example you mentioned you know mentoring somebody.
or training somebody you can't just sort of show up at somebody's desk and say I'm gonna mentor you now.
so you would need help on that but the other things like be more productive.
or you know manage a bigger portfolio you can ask you know can I I'd like to take on this project so that I have a deeper portfolio.
or you may find that there's some reporting that that the next job up from yours there's some reports you know monthly reports that that role creates.
and presents to management.
and you can start just creating those reports a lot of times with data that you can get you know from inside the company.
so there's the the stuff that you can do on your own.
and in that case you've got a list of things that you need to do other things you could do on your own.
and so you begin you know just executing on those things how do I get those things done.
but you'll also find as you mentioned some things that you just can't do on your own like mentoring or working with large enterprise clients.
you can't just kind of go grab one of those you may need it assigned to you.
and so you have to kind of put your hat in the ring and so that's when you would collaborate with your manager.
and let your manager know hey by the way I'm interested in being promoted to this other job.
and I can see what the responsibilities are for that job I see that it requires me to manage a large enterprise project.
so can you help me get assigned to a large enterprise project in the next 90 days or the next one that comes in.
and ask your manager to help give you those things.
or I see that it requires me to mentor money I know these two junior developers were just hired and I'd be happy to mentor them.
can you help me arrange that is it okay if if you introduce me to those two junior developers.
and I can begin mentoring them to kind of get that under my belt.
so you'll have to go to your manager and kind of collaborate the alternative would be you know kind of.
like I said like sort of just dropping by somebody's desk and saying I'm gonna mentor you.
not because I want to get promoted I don't think that would go over very well.
so those things again asking your manager for support it's good because one they'll have a heads up you're pursuing a promotion that's good for them to know.
and two you'll be asking for their help enlisting their help to do those things.
so that now you're collaborating on the things you're trying to do to get promoted.
so now you've kind of ringing them onto your team and asking for their help which should be beneficial to you.
yeah as I hear that with my manager ears I cannot imagine telling someone no.
you can't help mentor no you can't help train no you can't work on this kind of project.
you're not asking me for money you're asking me for something that's entirely within my realm of ability to grant.
and you're showing me that you're motivated which is enormous ly important to me as a manager.
Josh this has been really interesting I really appreciate your coming on today.
what have I forgotten to ask about negotiation that people need to know.
gosh that's a really good question Marcus I don't think you've forgotten to ask anything.
I kind of you know I talk about the subject a lot and.
so I I can't think of any topics that we didn't get to that I think are crucial topics for people.
I think your questions enabled me to kind of hit on all the all the good highlights.
so I think I don't think there's anything that I can think of I think we we hit all the really good points.
and I think everybody listening should now have kind of a good idea of how to negotiate an interview when changing companies.
but also how to how to move up a level in terms of salary or job responsibilities at your current company.
great Josh where can people find you online where can they find your book.
great so I'll start with where you can find me and then give you to two places that you can find my book. and some some stuff that I think will be really useful to your listener.
so you can find me on twitter i'm at josh duty on twitter easy to find and I'm on there I'm pretty active and I'm also on LinkedIn.
so if you look for Josh duty on LinkedIn I'm there.
my book is at fearless salary negotiation dot-com.
and I also have a free promotion course for getting promoted at work at work that walks through that process it's an email course.
and you can find that at job promotion course.com.
I think that might be particularly useful.
I know you know most people listening to this probably thought you know how to interview and how to negotiate was pretty interesting but I'm not doing that anytime soon.
but most people are probably at work and they're thinking I would like to explore you know.
how do I move to that next job how do i how do I get more responsibilities.
and so job promotion course comm will get you to a free seven-day email course that you can take.
and to walk through the process that I described with a worksheet and some other good some other good resources too.
Josh thank you so much for showing for being with us today.
thanks for having me Marcus it was a lot of fun.
getting software to your users quickly and reliably is the most important part of being a software engineer.
snap C is cloud-based continuous integration and continuous deployment tool lets you set up in minutes with your github account.
and within a few clicks we'll have your first pipeline running.
discover and fix your bugs quickly before pushing the production by setting up stages from simple ones to complex that run automatically when you push your changes.
need more speed run tests in parallel with expanded workers and get your feedback fast.
deploy to Heroku AWS and more we even integrate with slack to give you updates on your builds.
go to snap CI slash software radio and build test and deploy free for 30 days.
snap CI embodies the lessons the thought works has learned from 20 years of software deployment the same lessons that have been written about by Martin Fowler and J's humble.
check it out at snap CI slash software radio.
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an educational program brought to you by I Triple E software magazine.
for more information about the podcast including other episodes visit our website @ SC - radioman.
to provide feedback you can write comments on each episode on the website or write a review on itunes mention a message us on twitter at SC radio.
or search for the software engineering radio group on LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook.
you can also email us at team @ SC - radio net.
this and all other episodes of SU radio is licensed under the creative commons two-point-five license. thanks again for your support.
[Music]
[Applause]
you.
[Music]